Hey everyone, welcome back to the
channel. I hope you guys are doing
extremely well. So today we will be
solving an interesting problem that is
you have to design a BST IT trader. Now
what is what is this uh designing BST
iterator? So you'll be given uh some
steps and you have to perform that. Now
the first step the first step will be
definitely that you'll be given a BST
iterator with the root. So this seven
will be basically a node which will be
containing seven. So that represents
that you have a root with a entire BST.
So at the first step you'll be given
okay you're given a root of the tree
that is the binary search tree. So
that's the first step. So you're done
with the first step. Next you will be
asked hey what is next? Now let me
explain you uh the stuffs. So there'll
be couple of stuffs. One is next. The
other one is has next. So let me explain
you first what does this signifies then
I I can move uh forward. Now if you
write the in order traversal yes if you
write the in order traversal that's uh
that that will be 3 7 9 15 20 for this
particular BST for this particular BST
the in order traversal will be this. So
whenever I say next so initially the
pointer will be pointing to a null like
it is pointing to a non-existent value
the moment I say next you should be
returning three okay next when I say
next you should be returning seven
whenever I say next 9 15 next 20 and
whenever I say has next assume you're
standing at 20 assume you were standing
at 20 and if I ask has next has Next
then you'll say no no no next got it
next means initially you are starting
with a non-existent next will be the
inordest guy next the next inordest guy
next the next inordest guy okay so for
an example if I explain you you're given
this particular binary search tree with
the root seven the first the moment they
say next it will be three because that
is the first next again whenever they
say next it'll definitely be Seven.
Whenever they say has next, so you're
currently standing at seven. Does it
have any other next? Yes, it does have.
So true. Now again you say next. So
you'll be like yes. The next is nine.
Has next. Yes. True. Again you're saying
next. So that will be 15. Does it have
next? Yes.
What's the next? 20. Has next. False.
because it does not have any next after
20 that thereby has next will be false.
So this is what you have to design a
class of functions such that this
particular functions are operated. Okay.
So how do you how do you operate these
particular functions? any idea any sort
of idea now the first thing that comes
to your mind is okay driver whenever
you're given BST iterator uh why don't
we keep a vector I think yeah that makes
sense uh we will keep a vector where we
will be storing uh the inorder traversal
okay so we're going to store all the
inorder traversal and we're going to
initially have the pointer over here
whenever someone says next I'm going to
just return it and then move the pointer
ahead. Whenever someone again says next,
I'm going to return it and move the
pointer ahead. Has next. Is this pointer
pointing to a value? If it is yes or
else false. So I can store the in order
and then next has net becomes has next
becomes very easy. But what is the time
complexity? It'll be BGO of one in order
to return the next as well as has next.
But the space complexity will be big of
n because you'll be storing the entire
in order traversal. I repeat because
you'll be storing the entire in order
traversal. The space complexity taken
will be big go of n. It looks a very
straightforward one like if you are
allowed to store the in order it looks a
very straightforward one. But the moment
I say no you're not allowed to store the
in order one then there is a problem.
Then there lies the problem. Now if you
remember well if you remember when uh
what is in order? in order was left then
node then right. That is what you always
did like you went into the extreme left
and the the moment you reach null then
the first node will be your inorders
like in order traversals first guy then
right after this you moved on to it
right and then to left that is what you
kept on doing rights again you started
going on left so can I borrow the logic
from that stuff that in in recussion or
in the in order traversal it was left
node and then right. So basically you
went to left first node. Okay after that
right and the left. So we're going to
borrow that logic and you're going to do
the same thing because they have asked
us to solve this problem in b of h space
where h is the height of the tree and
they've said key next and has next can
be easily done in bogo of like one on
average one on average sometimes it
might take up more than one but on an
average you have to take b of one so
throughout it will be if you add up all
of them it should be bogo of one. So the
time complexity has to be this and the
space complexity has to be this. You
have to design an algorithm. Okay. So
it's time that we think of an algorithm.
So let's come up with an algorithm. So
remember in order to design this
algorithm you have to write a
constructor. Now the constructor will be
given the BST iterator and that will be
initially the root which is as of now
seven. So whenever that's given to you,
what you will do is you will take a
stack data structure. Yes, you're going
to take a stack data structure. So what
is a stack data structure? It is last in
first out. If you remember well last in
first out the guy who gets in last comes
out first. So you're going to use a
stack data structure. Now whenever a BST
iterator of seven is given you have to
remember you have to remember one thing
that it is left node and right. So every
time you go to extreme left. Okay. So if
you're given seven, if you're given
seven in the constructor, what you will
do is you will take seven and you'll go
to the extreme. Yes, I repeat, you will
go to the extreme left and put
everything into the stack. So let's do
that. So seven is what I put. What is
seven's left? Three. What's three is
left? Two. What two is left? One. You
take up all the elements of seven. Seven
left and put it into the stack. That is
what you will always do. Perfect. Next.
There was assume there is a next. The
moment someone says next that means in
orders first element as of now because
this is the first time next is being
called. So what you will do is you will
say okay who is text first element take
it out. That will be my next. But wait
what was in order? Whenever you take out
note, you go to its right. You go to its
right. But as of now, right of one is
nothing. Right of one is nothing. So you
don't take anything. Perfect. Next.
Again a next is called
this time stack as two. So you take out
two.
Does two have a right? No. So there is
no right traversal as of now. Amazing.
Next again. Next is called. This time
you take out three. Here comes the
twist. The moment you take out three,
three is taken out. Three has a right.
So you go to right and you put
everything into the stack. You go to
right and you put everything into the
stack. So again the same way six 5 4
because right will be called that's six.
And again the same procedure of left
left 6 5 4 will be inserted. So if you
observe it carefully, you're actually
following the in order using this
particular stack. So it's an iterative
in order that you are currently doing.
Just making sure that you only store the
h the height height order elements.
Perfect. Next. If someone comes up and
says, hey, do you have an has next? Do
you have next? That's very easy to
answer. If your stack if your stack is
non-MPT, which in this case stack has
multiple elements. So I be like hey dude
listen I still have elements. So that's
going to be true. So the stack is empty
that that becomes very simple. You say
true. Next time whenever an call like
next comes again very straightforward.
You pick up four and you give it. Does
four have a right? I don't see four
having a right. I definitely don't see
four having a right. So no right. Next
you pick up five. Does five have a
right? No. Next
you pick up six.
Does six have a right? No. Next
you pick up seven.
But does seven are right? Yes. Insert
all of them. 10 9 8 inserted. Go to
right. Go to right and insert all the
left. Go to right and insert all the
left. So if there is a right like seven
has a right. So take all of these guys
and insert into the stack. That is what
you'll do because that's very obvious.
Left node then right. Whenever you go to
the right then again left.
That logic is being used. Perfect. Next
called so eight you got. Next called
nine you got. And remember none of them
none of them have rights. So again next
called 10. Now this is the moment the
stack becomes empty and if someone calls
has next you can say false. Yes you can
say false. That's how you can easily
design this particular data structure.
So if I talk about the time complexity
uh I can say that space complexity is
definitely big of h as the height of the
tree because I'm just storing left left
at at any instance. I'm not storing a
lot of elements and the time complexity
will be big go of one on average not on
every call because you're pushing left
left but sometimes you're not pushing a
lot of times you're not pushing so if
you average it out there are n elements
there are n elements so you'll be
pushing on n elements correct you'll be
pushing on n elements in total and there
might be n next calls there might be n
next calls so n by n on average is b of
one because if you're pushing n elements
throughout out put a across all you're
pushing n elements and there are n next
calls so on average per single call it
will be b go of one that that is that is
the reason I can easily see the time
complexity on average is b of one and
the space complexity is b of h that is
how you can easily design this bst
iterator so it's time to discuss the C++
as well as the java code as usual is on
the left and the java code is on the
right. Both are extremely identical. So
I'll just be discussing the C++. You can
follow the Java code on the right. So
what I what I've done is initially I
have declared a stack. You can just
declare it private so that it's a member
function. So you can just declare it uh
private. Yeah. And so I've declared a
stack of tree nodes because I have to
store all the tree nodes in a stack. And
uh this is the constructor. Now whenever
you're given root, so if you remember
when I was given the root, what did I
do? I took the root and every left into
the stack. Remember? So I call the push
all. Now push all's duty push all's duty
is to take all the lefts and push it
onto the stack. Stack push and all the
lefts. Push all means I'll give him a
node and I'll push all the lefts into
the stack. That is what push all's duty
is. So he does that whenever you're
given the constructor. Next has next.
How is the has next function written?
It's very simple. If the stack is non-
empty, you say I I do have elements.
Simple as that. If the stack is empty, I
don't have elements. As simple as that,
right? Next one is something which is
the stuff. I want the next guy of in
order like the pointer is pointing to.
So what I do is I know the stack top
element is the next guy. That's for sure
we discussed, right? Because if you're
going left, left, left, the last guy is
the smallest element. So you just pick
it up top and then you pop it off the
stack. Now if you remember if there does
exist a right you go to the right and
push all the left. Remember you go to
the right and you push all the left. So
you go to the right and push all does
your that job pushing all the left. So
push all will push all the left. And
once you have done this you just needed
the value. So the temp node that you
have taken out over here you can just
return it. As simple as that. Now this
is how the C++ code will look like. And
similarly is how the Java code will also
look like. So guys, I hope you have
understood the entire explanation as
well as the C++ and the Java solution.
Just in case you did, please please
please make sure you like this video and
if you are new to this channel, do
consider subscribing and yeah, with this
I'll be wrapping up this video. Let's
meet in the next one. Bye-bye. Take
care.
[Music]
Forget you're golden.